Theater Collection, 1870-1982
Sophia Smith Collection
Theater collection
1870-1982
MS 450
12 boxes (7 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
The collection documents the work of women in the performing arts, especially American actresses, women playwrights, and dancers. There are biographical files on individuals; articles and dissertations; several contemporary plays by women; and printed material on women filmmakers and feminist theater.
The collection documents the work of women in the performing arts, especially American actresses, women playwrights, and dancers. There are biographical files on individuals such as Maude Adams, Joan Crawford, Bette Davis, Doris Day, Marlene Dietrich, Isadora Duncan, Cloris Leachman, Ida Lupino, Tatum O'Neal, Mary Pickford, Lillian Russell, Marlo Thomas, and Cicely Tyson, among others. Articles and dissertations include topics related to women in theater and dance, including biographical writings on Hallie Flanagan, Lillian Helman, Katherine Cornell, Eva LeGallienne, Olive Logan, Alla Nazimova, Cornelia Otis Skinner, and Ruth St. Denis. Also included are several contemporary plays by women, and printed material on women filmmakers and feminist theater.
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following exceptions:
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
This collection has not been fully processed; therefore it may be difficult to use.
Material in this collection may be protected by copyright and it is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy all copyright holders. Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.
Periodic additions are expected.
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Flanagan, Hallie, 1890-1969--Biography--Sources; St. Denis, Ruth, 1880-1968--Biography--Sources; Hellman, Lillian, 1906- --Biography--Sources; Cornell, Katharine, 1893-1974--Biography--Sources; Le Gallienne, Eva, 1899- --Biography--Sources; Nazimova, 1879-1945--Biography--Sources; Skinner, Cornelia Otis, 1901- --Biography--Sources; Actors--United States--Biography--Sources; Actresses--United States--Biography--Sources; Dancers--United States--Biography--Sources; Feminist theater--United States--History--Sources; Theater--United States--History--Sources; Women dramatists, American--Biography--Sources; Women in motion pictures--History--Sources; Women in the performing arts--History--Sources; Women in the theater--United States--History--Sources; Women motion picture producers and directors--History--Sources
APPENDIX: Title List
Articles
Arant, Farilie. "America's 'First Man of the Stage' Thomas Cooper." John F. Kennedy Center Program Magazine, Oct.-Nov., 1971-72 season.
Cohen, Debra. Untitled article on the work of Meredith Monk
Herzel, Roger. Untitled article. Concerns English comedies of the 18th century, especially the changing role of the senex.
Hewitt, Barnard. "Mrs. John Wood and the Lost Art of Burlesque Acting." Educational Theater Journal, vol. XIII, no. 2, May 1961
Jenkins, Linda Walsh. "Women in Performing Arts: An Overview."
Macer-Story, Eugenia. "Drama for Health: Principles, Sources and Modern Use of the 'Wu-p'o' Tradition." Eugenia Story, 1975
Magnus, Dorothy B. "Matriarchs of the Regional Theater." Delivered at the August, 1975 ATA Convention.
Matlack, Cynthia Sutherland. "On the Affinity between the Historiography of Theatre History and Women Studies." Preliminary Symposium: The Historiography of Theatre History, Ohio State University, April, 1974.
Wilmeth, Don Burton. "Margo Jones Theater." From his dissertation, University of Illinois: Department of Speech and Drama, 1964
Tapes
Leontovich, Eugenie. Chinoy Interview, 1968
Terry, Megan. May 1976, Smith College
"A Salute to Women in American Theatre." Florida State University, Tallahassee participants: Ann Burr, Celeste Holm, Audrey Wood, Dorothy Olim, Vinie Burrows, Ethel Barrymore Colt, Jean Dalrymple, Patricia Zippordt, Cheryl Crawford.
Plays
Albee, Gliria. Medea. 1973
Asher, Sandra Fenichel.
How I Nearly Changed the World, But Didn't (Not Yet Anyway).
Afterthoughts in Eden, 1972
Ausubel, Bobbi. Focus on Me.
Boesing, Martha
The Gelding, June 1974
Pimp, October 1974
Pimp, A One-Act Play for Three Women, November 1977
Brindley, Penelope. The Transformations.
Burnham, Sophy. Penelope, 1976
Caravan Theater, Cambridge, MA. How to Make a Woman.
Flanagan, Hallie and Clifford Margaret Ellen. Can you Hear Their Voices? 1931.
Gates, Joanne E. Aphra Behn: Playwright.
Gustafson, Anita. Aunt Ealdgyth is Coming Today! Stand Back!, 1975
LaTempa, Susan.
Ladies' Room. Suedan Press, 1975
A Play of One's Own…The Story of Virginia Woolf, 1974
The Receptionist. Suedan Press, 1975
Morris, Liz. Minnie's Last Jig, 1976
Nass, Elyse.. Love from the Madhouse, 1972
Presson, Jay. Stars in a Person's Backyard.
Terry, Megan. Approaching Simone, 1973
Thompson, Louise. Impressions of Loving.
Wilshire, Donna. A Revolution is a Circle, 1976.
Dissertations
Abrahamson, Irving. The Career of Rachel Corothers in the American Drama. University of Chicago: Department of English, 1956
Dodge, Caroline. Rosamond Gilder and the Theater. University of Illinois: Department of Theater, 1973
Epolito, Joseph. A Study of Characters in Selected Plays of William Inge. Ohio State University: Department of Theater, 1974
Hitchcock, Ned II. Dancing Ground: An approach to the Criticism of Modern Dance. Case Western Reserve University: Department of Theater, 1973
Humble, Alberta L. Matilda Heron, American Actress. University of Illinois: Department of Theater, 1959
Klein, Elaine S. The Development of the Leading Feminine Character in Selected Librettos of American Musicals from 1900 to 1960. Columbia University: Department of Education, 1962
Loganbill, G. Bruce. Cornelia Otis Skinner and Her Art Form of Monologue Drama. Michigan State: Department of Speech and Drama, 1961
McKerrow, Margaret. A Descrptive Study of the Acting of Alla Nazimova. San Diego State University: Department of Drama, 1961
Margetts, Ralph E. A Study of the Theatrical Career of Julia Dean Hayne. University of Utah: Department of Speech and Drama, 1959
Mendoza, Barbara. Hallie Flanagan. Her Role in American Theater 1924-1935. New York University: Arts Professions 1975
Moss, Lynda. An Historical Study of Katherine Cornell as an Actress - Producer: 1961-1960. University of Southern California: Department of Theater, 1972
Schaffer, Pauline Wright. The Position of Women in Society as Reflected in Serious American Drama from 1890-1928. Stanford University: Department of Speech and Drama, 1965
Schanke, Robert A. Eva LeGallienne--Actress, Director, Manager. University of Nebraska: Department of Theater, 1975
Schlundt, Christena Lindborg. The Role of Ruth St. Denis in the History of American Dance, 1906-1922. Claremont College: Department of Speech and Drama, 1958
Small, Miriam. The Life and Literary Relations of Charlotte LennoxThe Life and Literary Relations of Charlotte Lennox. Yale University: Department of English, 1945
Swain, James W. Mrs. Alexander Drake, A Biographical Study. Tulane University: Department of Theater, 1970
McPherson, Michael L. Lillian Hellman and Her Critics. University of Denver: Department of Theater, 1976
Kaplan, Zoe Coralnick. Women in Focus in Major Plays and Productions of Rachel Corothers. City University of New York, Ph.D., 1979, Theatre
Stephens, Judith Louise. The Central Female Characters in the Pulitzer Prize Plays, 1918-1949. Kent State University: Graduate College, 1977, Ph.D.
- General and miscellaneous
  - Bibliography and note cards circa 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Women Playwrights and correspondence 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chinoy: flyer, activities list, pamphlets, and newsletter 1975-82 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and mailing 1975-79 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dance: clippings and memo 1854-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Helen Duberstein: clippings 1972-76 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Actors & Actresses: photographs 1888-90 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Toulouse-Lautrec: postcards undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Film
  - Catalogs
    - Serious Business Company, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Women and their Sexuality in the New Film, by Joan Mellen 1973 (Box 2)
    - Women's Films in Print, by Bonnie Dawson circa 1975 (Box 2)
    - Workprint 1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Flyers, pamphlets, and correspondence 1972-81 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Flyers, newsletters, clippings, correspondence, and pamphlets 1962-73 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Handbook, programs, and pamphlets 1972-75 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Pamphlets, flyers, and articles 1973-81 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Stage
  [see also: Employment Collection for script of play by Elizabeth McFadden- The Product of the Mill (1912)- on shelf]
  - Scrapbook: clippings and photographs 1929-31 (Box 3)
  - Clippings 1969-79 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - General Articles 1855-1929 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Newsletter and address labels 1975-81 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Reviews, pamphlet, clippings, and scripts 1971-80 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Guerilla Theatre: pamphlets undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - I Woman: stories, poster, scripts, and poems 1961-70 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Feminist Theater
    - Pamphlets, play, calendar, and correspondence 1975-85 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - General: pamphlets, poster, articles, and programs 1972-75 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Performers
  - Adams, Maude
    - Photographs, clippings, and correspondence 1900-57 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Script undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Anderson, Mary: photographs, clippings, correspondence, and book 1877-95 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Barnett, Margo: pamphlet undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Bernhart, Sarah: photographs, clippings, and pamphlets 1891-1922 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Bloom, Claire: clippings 1971 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Cayvan, Georgia: clippings 1884-86 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Connard, Phyllis (with Lynn Fontanne) (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Crabtree, Lotta: clippings undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Crawford, Joan: photograph and clipping 1978 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Davis, Bette: photograph and clippings 1978 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Day, Doris: clipping undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Dietrich, Marlene: photograph and clipping 1977 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Draper, Ruth: clippings and correspondence 1954-57 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Duncan, Isadora: clipping ,1927 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Duse, Eleonora: articles, pamphlets, photograph, and clippings 1896-1924 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Elssler, Franzisca (Fanny), Ballet dancer: "letters and journal" 1845 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Enters, Angna: programs and clippings 1933-46 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Espert, Nuria: clippings 1972 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Faucit, Helen: scrapbook 1917 (Box 4, Folder 40a)
  - Fiske, Minnie Maddern: clippings, correspondence, and photograph 1924-32 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Fonda, Jane: clippings 1970-71 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Gerstenberg, Alice: articles 1947-48 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Alice Gerstenberg Experimental Theatre Workshop: book 1958 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Gordon, Ruth: clipping 1973-76 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Gregory, Augusta Persse Lady: clippings 1860-1932 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Hamlin, Joanne: pamphlets, programs, clippings, and photographs 1976 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Harris, Julia Ann (Julie): clippings and magazine 1955-79 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Havoc, June: photographs, Early Havoc, clippings 1959, [see also Books on Shelf] (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Hayes, Helen: clipping 1975 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Hellman, Lillian: articles and clippings 1975-76 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Holzer, Adela: clippings 1975 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Jackson, Glenda: clippings 1971 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Kendal, Madhe: photograph 1889 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Kennedy, Edith Wynne: correspondence undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Lamb, Myrna: articles, clippings, and pamphlet 1970-71 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Lasser, Louise: clipping 1976 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Leachman, Cloris: clipping 1975 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Leontovich, Eugenie: clipping 1972 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Loden, Barbara: clipping 1970 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Logan, Olive, [see also Books on Shelf] (Box 5)
  - Lupino, Ida: clippings 1974 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Marlowe, Julia: photograph, article, and correspondence 1892 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Marsh, Jean: clipping 1974 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Mather, Margaret: photograph undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Meader, Clara Fisher: clipping 1897 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Mercouri, Melina: clippings 1971 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Morris, Clara, [see Morris] (Box 5)
  - O'Neal, Tatum: clippings 1973 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Pavowa, Anna: clippings 1931 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Pickford, Mary: clippings and correspondence 1937-79 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Rachel (Elisa Felix): correspondence and clippings 1843-1913 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Rehan, Ada: correspondence and A Daughter of Comedy 1891 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Robinor, Hanna: photograph undated (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Russell, Anna: The Power of Being a Positive Stinker with LP record 1955 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Russell, Lillian: clippings 1922 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Seeback, Marie: memoir 1891 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Siddons, Sarah: photograph, clipping, and article 1845 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Terry, Ellen: articles and clippings 1907-58, [see also Garrison photographs] (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Thomas, Marlo: clippings 1975 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Tyson, Cicely: clipping 1978 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Ward, Genevieve: memoir 1863, [see also letter in N.E. Hospital Collection] (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Webster, Margaret: programs 1964 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Audio tapes (Box 6)
    - #1 Cheryl Crawford (Box 6)
    - #2 Celeste Holm, Ann Burr (Box 6)
    - #3 Megan Terry (Box 6)
    - #4 Ann Burr, Vinie Burrows, Ethyl Barrymore Colb, Dorothy Olim (Box 6)
  - Microfilm
    - #1. Humble, A.L.: Matilda Heron, American Actress, 1959 (Box 6)
    - #2. James Walton Swain, Dept. of Theatre & Speech, Tulane University: Mrs. Alexander Drake, A Biographical Study 1970 (Box 6)
    - #3. Loganbill, G. Bruce: Cornelia Otis Skinner and her Art Form of Monologue (Box 6)
  - Articles and pamphlets
    - General, 1961-76 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - Matriarchs of the Regional Theatre 1975 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - A Salute to Women in Theatre, the Charles Macarthur Center for American Theatre (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Drama for Health, by E. Macer Story (Box 6)
    - Mattack, Cynthia S.: On the Affinity Between the Historiography of Theatre History and Women Studies 1974 (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Settlement House Theatre: Community & Theatrical Transformations, Sonja Enloe 1982 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - PhD theses
    - Rosamond Gilder and the Theatre, by C. Dodge 1975 (Box 7)
    - A Study of Character in Selected Plays of William Inge: Come Back…J. Epolito 1974 (Box 7)
    - The Career of Rachel Corothers in the American Drama, by I. Abrahmson 1956 (Box 7)
    - The Development of the Leading Feminine Character in Selected Librettos of American…, by E. Klein 1962 (Box 7)
    - A Descriptive Study of the Acting of Alla Nazimova, by M. McKerrow 1974 (Box 7)
    - The Role of Ruth St. Denis in the History of American Dance, 1906-1922, by C. Schlundt 1958 (Box 7)
    - Hallie Flanagan: Her Role in American Theatre, 1924-1935, by B. Mendoza1976,volume I (Box 7)
    - Dancing Ground: An Approach to the criticism of the Modern Dance, by N. Hitchcock II (Box 8)
    - Lillian Hellman and Her Critics, by M. L. McPherson (Box 8)
    - Hallie Flanagan: Her Role in American Theatre, 1924-1935, by B. Mendoza1976, volume II (Box 8)
    - Women In Focus in Major Plays and Productions of Rachel Corothers, by Z. Kaplan 1979 (Box 9)
  - Leontovich/Chinoy Interview: IBM belts 1968 (Box 10)
  - Plays, contemporary
    - Asher, Sandra Fenichel (Box 11)
      - Afterthoughts in Eden 1974 (Box 11)
      - How I Nearly Changed the World, but Didn't (Not Yet, Anyway) (Box 11)
    - Focus On Me, by Bobbi Ausubel 1974 (Box 11)
    - Boesing, Martha (Box 11)
      - The Gelding 1974 (Box 11)
      - Pimp 1977 (Box 11)
    - Penelope, by Sophy Burnham 1976 (Box 11)
    - Can You Hear Their Voices?, Vassar Experimental Theatre. (Box 11)
    - Aunt Ealdygyth is Coming Today! Stand Back!, by Anita Gustafson 1975 (Box 11)
    - Both Ancient and Modern, by J. Gates undated (Box 12)
    - Susan LaTempa (Box 12)
      - A Play of One's Own…The Story of Virginia Woolf 1974 (Box 12)
      - Wanda Winner 1975 (Box 12)
    - Minnie's Last Jig, by L. Morris 1976 (Box 12)
    - Love from the Madhouse: A One-Act Play, by E. Nass 1972 (Box 12)
    - Stars in a Person's Backyard, by Jay Presson (Box 12)
    - Approaching Simone, by M. Terry 1973 (Box 12)
    - Impression of Loving, by Louise Thompson (Box 12)
    - Donna Wilshire (Box 12)
      - A Revolution is a Circle 1976 (Box 12)
      - Daughters of Liberty 1976 (Box 12)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Portraits reproduced from the Sophia Smith Collection: Great Ladies of the Theatre undated (Map-case Flat file)
  - Miscellaneous photographs of actors, playbills, and circus bills 1851, 1858, undated (Map-case Flat file)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - Havoc, June, Early Havoc 1959
  - Logan, Olive, Before the Footlights and Behind the Scenes 1870
  - Margetts, Ralph E., A Study of the Theatrical Career of Julia Dan Hayne 1959
  - Moffat, Marjorie, The One Woman Show 1935
  - Moss, Linda T., A Historical Sketch of Katharine Cornell as an Actress-Producer, 1931-1960 1974, (2 copies)
  - Schanke, Robert A., Eva Le Gallienne: First Lady of Repertory 1975
  - Small, Miriam R., Charlotte Ramsay Lennox 1935
  - Stephens, Judith L., The Central Female Characters in the Pulitzer Prize Plays, 1918-1949 1977